all right here we go everybody wave wave
to YouTube hi YouTube we are going to
talk about something called batch and a
few of you are like what the hell is
batch okay so the first thing we need to
talk about is what it is batch is the
use of um a job CU we'll call it to
submit long running this is the key long
running jobs to a system and then watch
it and then take its output and do
something with output raise your hand if
you can think or suggest some things
that in 2024 lend themselves to this
pattern I don't think it's a surprise to
tell anybody that machine
learning data modeling crunching of data
creation of data model jobs you know
putting a data you know creating data
models that then can be used and
integrated into things in 2024 I mean
it's all machine learning has has
clearly clearly dominated the IT
industry across the board and the batch
pattern is the primary way to fulfill
the needs of jobs that have to take a
day a week two weeks sometimes and that
are running on you know sometimes multi
thousand Hardware uh from Nvidia and
stuff like that so the the concept of
batch of submitting a job to a system
goes way back to the 70s in the dawn of
Computing when we were doing mainframes
now I I have a punch card um you know my
grandpa used to used to have jobs called
computer operator and they were the only
people allowed to put the The Punch
Cards into the computer because you know
touching the computer was like hands off
people are like you know arguing about
keyboards in 2024 and back then you
didn't even have access to the point is
that this pattern has been around
forever why because the idea even
outside of computing of having having
a you know a system of some kind working
on something and chugging away at it and
then producing output and being able to
monitor that that's been around forever
and you know whether whether you were
smoothing stones for some reason and you
know I mean there's a milli okay so it's
it's not so much that batch is an
innovation so much as that the the
pattern meets the needs of machine
learning teams and that includes the
Enterprise um so what does this have to
do with Cloud native um and so I the
this the Catalyst for this video is
actually uh this this article that I
that came across my my desk the
kubernetes turns 10 what's going to go
on with Cloud native um Cloud native
kubernetes is a cloud native
architecture here's kind of the Crux of
it kubernetes and the whole Cloud native
ethos feels a little bit tired um
somebody inside of our of our community
said kubernetes has just passed through
the Gartner hype cycle which I will let
you Google but basically it's that as
technology becomes popular it goes way
up everybody's using it they're all
hyping it up and then it kind of falls
into the trough of disillusionment I
mean Garder probably is making millions
of dollars right now just by you know
people saying this and then people kind
of you know the reality it kind of comes
out of the reality you know and and
people kind of get to the you know this
is what it's really good at if it if it
survives right sometimes things fall off
the the thing and they never come back
like such as virtual worlds for example
just to throw something out there um and
which is interesting because now any
know I can go down that path I'm not
going to kubernetes did what what does
kubernetes do kubernetes is came about
because of the whole problem with
Services what is a service a lot of you
might already know this but I I'm going
to you know if you're absolute novice
you don't know what it is a service in
the it sense is many things but
primarily in the it you know Department
sense a service is a web server usually
that's running that's answering
responses so it's a request response
kind of situation sometimes it'll keep
open the channel but ultimately it's a
request response kind of thing that's
why you have a server involved you have
clients that are requesting it and
they're saying I want a thing do this
thing for me and while it is true that
you can use a service as architecture
like that to you know I want to request
starting a job and then have something
on the back end do its thing and then
keep checking in on it which is actually
the API that we wrote for our batch
system which I'll get to then you know
you you but most of the time when you're
talking about a service you're talking
about a query what's the weather like
what's the GPS of that plane what's you
know that's the kind of thing and um
some of you may not know that Amazon
sort of champion the idea of the
microservice um beos has given credit
for that even though it was a concept
that predates him by several years
um but the the idea of saying okay
everything in our Enterprise is going to
be one of these going going to be
there's going to be ultimately there's
going to be a web server in there
answering requests right and since that
time you know Services have taken many
different forms they not even
necessarily HTTP which is the web
sometimes they also use um you know grpc
which is a reference kind of to an older
thing called RPC I mean I've been around
long enough to see this idea of of
services and distributed applications uh
which is the broader term um you know
have many different forms and and and
the reason I say this is because there's
this you know as as the the the it World
Went Crazy breaking everything up into
microservices they all suddenly realized
oh damn we broken we broken up
everything so much we have no way to you
know centrally manage it so you started
getting these Concepts called meshes
that are organizing all the services and
you know about that you know in in that
time frame that's when kubernetes came
about which used to be called Borg if
some of you don't know this kubernetes
used to be called Borg it was it was
Google's own internal thing for managing
microservices within Google uh which
Google ultimately and very slowly
decided to release to the to the world
and we got to read all their horrible uh
very very early go code that looks like
a bunch of java thrown together by
people who have no idea how to write any
go code the kubernetes codebase is
abysmally bad do not use it as an
example of how to write go code whether
or not that's because they did it so
long ago or not I don't that's a
different question I won't I won't beat
him up over that but the the point is is
the kubernetes is the is the you know
the the primary thing um and as an
engineer four years ago when I got hired
to do kubernetes infrastructure
engineering for a machine learning group
kubernetes was all the rage um in fact I
was specifically tasked with um looking
at things like implementing Jupiter
notebooks inside of kubernetes and going
through Jupiter Hub and all these
different things to facilitate our
machine learning people and um to tell
you the truth um I me at one point we
were trying to shoehorn these big big
batch jobs um into kubernetes we were
going to use kubernetes as the
replacement for our you know very old uh
batch processing system which was
implemented in a technology called PBS
uh that was originally implemented by
NASA a lot of people don't even know
about this everybody's heard about
kubernetes nobody has heard about open
PBS and I am going to tell you about it
I'm trying to find it here um let me see
if I can find it so let's find open
PBS open
PBS
um there we go so this why is open PBS
even something that I'm going to talk
about this is not a kids channel no no
um so this is open PPS has transferred
hands a few times um and the industry
leading workload manager on job
scheduler for high performance Computing
so what is high performance Computing
HPC it's called that that is high
performance Computing is at the core of
machine learning because high
performance Computing is what is
enabling the machine learning models to
finish in Faster times which equals more
money for the Enterprise Etc so so HPC
high performance Computing is really
really key uh to ml in fact in my
organization the organization is
literally called HBC ml because they're
Associated so closely with one another
and they will be for the foreseeable
future with the goal of getting those
models and by the way I wish I could
talk to you please don't tell where I
work but the the rather boring company
that I work for is doing things with
their models with their machine learning
models that would blow your mind one of
days one of these days I'm going to be
able to talk about what they're doing um
but but using using you know visual
integration and other things they can
control systems uh consumer systems that
you would know immediately um and have
them do things that you you cannot even
possibly imagine if you haven't been
following what's possible with in in the
consumer realm uh with high performance
Computing and machine learning then you
know you want to look into it
particularly if you're looking at it a
job in Tech so and and you know Again
full disclosure I do you know
infrastructure engineering I spend a lot
of time Cod and go and the what we're
doing is we're enabling
submission and our applications live in
kubernetes as a microservice in order to
provide the web front eye front end and
the UI and the rest API endpoints using
AP all of these things you know served
up with Jin they're all coming from our
developers our Vel opers are sending
these rather large very important
machine learning jobs to these you know
extremely
expensive
um ultimately it's extremely expensive
gpus which are associated with these
compute nodes which are which by the way
a node if you've been if you come from
the kubernetes world a node has never
just been about kubernetes a node is a a
machine in this case that is dedicated
to doing a particular thing um as a
primary responsibility and you can bring
them up and down and you can cluster
them together and this is exactly how
kubernetes manages microservices uh by
you know clustering nodes and stuff but
the concept of a node goes far far back
you know more back than than just
kubernetes and so you have these very
very large um systems that are designed
to run jobs for a very long time and to
report on those things and so systems
like open PBS are there to help do those
things and the main takeaway from this
video is to tell you that while you
might think kubernetes is the thing to
learn to get the job today and it
probably is if you're going to go into
infrastructure engineering especially if
you're supporting there's a good chance
that the applications themselves are
going to be deployed to kubernetes or
something like it um because it just
handles you know the what happens if I
have I need three or four web service at
the same time that's what microservices
and and kubernetes are good they're good
for doing but but something like PBS is
designed to actually do the grunt work
and so I just want to make sure that you
don't
leave processing and understanding batch
systems such as open PBS from your
educational path if you're going to go
into Enterprise it because chances are
that you haven't heard about it yet and
that you are also going to hear a lot
about machine learning jobs and how to
submit them and process them and there
are many many um Solutions out there I'm
not going to name some of them that
we've had horrible experience with but
there are lots of solutions that are
more and more there catering and Cloud
solutions that are catering to this and
there is kind of a side quest here and
that is how do you deal with the amount
of CPU that's required to process some
of these jobs um we have had people
within our organization
um think that they wanted to go to the
cloud and I won't I won't point out what
cloud but they went with the cloud and
they tried to do some of these crunching
these job crunching on these data model
jobs and they paid through the nose for
the money there and so you know renting
renting a GPU from Nvidia for $2,000 a
month is nothing compared to the costs
that some of these people are paying
through the cloud so you know the rush
to the cloud makes sense when it comes
to things like you know get operations
and inner source and and ex you know
expanding you know the the cicd
offerings of services and the building
of and release of software it's still a
very important part of the it Enterprise
and it always will be but and when it
comes to cloud cloud is not going to be
the solution for handling batch
processing I predicted if it hasn't
already become a reality for most
companies out there that this batch
processing that's being driven by
Machine learning which is taking over
every aspect of it is going to continue
to to push the need for on Prem
affordable solutions for batch
processing and the organizations that
are that are seeing this they're the
ones that are winning they're the ones
that are that are that are you know and
it's it's interesting because it's
bringing a lot of the same factors are
at play that that promoted the use of
the Mainframe and I I'm an old I never
was really a Mainframe guy but I'm
extremely fascinated by the possibility
of returning to more Mainframe
processing and as the mainframes they
won't look like the mainframes of the
past they'll look more like clusters of
nodes that they can be sliced up but the
but people on the Mainframe have been
slicing up virtual machines I mean the
Mainframe invented logical volume
manager the Mainframe has been slicing
up massive amounts of compute power into
little you know chunks nodes Linux
machines whatever you want they've been
doing that since the 70s I mean or late
80s anyway so you know they they they
know how to do this stuff meanwhile we
have companies coming onto the scene
like oxide who are you know doing
essentially the same thing with physical
hardware and they're selling they're
selling you you know a cluster of actual
nodes you know and and we're starting to
see this but there at some point a
hardware vendor like IBM or anyone of
the Mainframe Benders is going to be
like you know what it's actually more
efficient for us to send you sell you
one big piece of computing power and
then let you divide it up the way you
want to I mean it's going to be
interesting and why is this video even
here because I am you know fond of
making videos that that attempt to
predict the future in a way that can
help you you know know what to know what
to learn and and I'm going to tell you
right now make sure you include batch
processing and the idea of what it takes
to do batch processing um which includes
understanding uh Technologies boring
technologies that no one's talking about
like open PBS and you know Linux as well
because that's almost all of it's going
to be on Linux that's all